Sidney Robertson Cowell Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Sidney Robertson Cowell Collection 1901-1992 (bulk 1936-1990)
ML31.C78
Cowell, Sidney Robertson
5067 items 29 containers 13 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Sidney Robertson Cowell (1903-1995) was a folksong and ethnic music collector and recordist, ethnographer, ethnomusicologist, teacher, writer, and wife of composer Henry Cowell. The collection consists of her personal papers which document all aspects of her life and work. The collection includes correspondence relating to personal and professional matters; fieldwork reports, fieldnotes, song lists and other materials from her field recording projects and trips; articles, essays, reviews, and papers written by Sidney Robertson Cowell; articles and narratives by and about Henry Cowell; autobiographical narratives and essays, clippings, family histories and other materials relating to her professional career and personal life; photographs; teaching materials; and song sheets and song books. In addition, the collection contains photocopies of a selection of Henry Cowell holographs, several annotated by Sidney Robertson Cowell, and a selection of folk songs with piano settings by Henry Cowell in his own hand.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Adams, Ansel, 1902-1984--Correspondence.; Bacon, Ernst, 1898-1990--Correspondence.; Bloch, Suzanne, 1907-2002--Correspondence.; Bronson, Bertrand Harris, 1902-1986--Correspondence.; Brown, Frank Clyde--Correspondence.; Cage, John--Correspondence.; Cowell, Henry, 1897-1965--Correspondence.; Cowell, Henry, 1897-1965--Photographs.; Cowell, Henry, 1897-1965.; Cowell, Henry, 1897-1965.; Cowell, Sidney Robertson--Archives.; Cowell, Sidney Robertson--Correspondence.; Cowell, Sidney Robertson--Ethnomusicological collections.; Cowell, Sidney Robertson--Photographs.; Cowell, Sidney Robertson.; Cowell, Sidney Robertson.; Dornbush, Adrian--Correspondence.; Eskin, Sam--Correspondence.; Ford, Warde H.; Franke, Grete--Correspondence.; Frankenstein, Alfred V. (Alfred Victor), 1906-1981--Correspondence.; Grainger, Percy, 1882-1961.; Grover, Carrie B.; Harrison, Lou, 1917-2003--Correspondence.; Hitchcock, H. Wiley (Hugh Wiley), 1923-2007--Correspondence.; Ives, Charles, 1874-1954.; Karpeles, Maud--Correspondence.; Kirkpatrick, John, 1905-1991--Correspondence.; Lichtenwanger, William, 1915-2000--Correspondence.; Lomax, John A. (John Avery), 1867-1948--Correspondence.; Maynor, Dorothy--Correspondence.; McPhee, Colin, 1900-1964--Correspondence.; Powell, Laurence, 1899-1990--Correspondence.; Saylor, Bruce--Correspondence.; Seeger, Charles, 1886-1979--Correspondence.; Seeger, Peggy, 1935- --Correspondence.; Seeger, Pete, 1919- --Correspondence.; Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1894-1995--Correspondence.; Spackman, Stephen--Correspondence.; Thomson, Virgil, 1896-1989--Correspondence.; Valiant, Margaret--Correspondence.; Van Hyning, Robert--Correspondence.; Weisgall, Hugo--Correspondence.; Wyner, Yehudi, 1929- --Correspondence.; Yuize, Shinʼichi--Correspondence.
Organizations
Archive of Folk Song (U.S.); United States. Farm Security Administration.; United States. Farm Security Administration.; United States. Resettlement Administration.; United States. Resettlement Administration.; W.P.A. California Folk Music Project Collection, 1938-1940 (Library of Congress); W.P.A. California Folk Music Project Collection, 1938-1940 (Library of Congress)
Subjects
Ballads, English--United States.; Ethnomusicologists--United States--Correspondence.; Field recordings--United States.; Folk dance music--United States.; Folk music--Appalachian Region.; Folk music--Asia.; Folk music--California.; Folk music--Canada.; Folk music--Ireland.; Folk music--Middle East.; Folk music--Middle West.; Folk music--Southern States.; Folk music--United States--History and criticism.; Folk music--United States.; Folk songs, English--Appalachian Region.; Folk songs, English--California.; Folk songs, English--Middle West.; Folk songs, English--Southern States.; Folk songs, English--United States.; Folk songs--California.; Folk songs--United States.; Political ballads and songs.; Protest songs.
Form/Genre
Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Drafts (Documents); Ethnography.; Field notes.; Memorandums.; Photographic prints.; Proposals.; Songbooks.; Songs (Document genre)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Sidney Robertson Cowell; 1977-1994.
Custodial History
The Library of Congress has enjoyed a long and mutually supportive relationship with Henry and Sidney Robertson Cowell that began in the 1930s and continued until Sidney’s death in 1995. Their donations to the Library have allowed researchers and scholars to study most of Henry Cowell’s music manuscripts, view materials that provide an exhaustive account of Sidney’s life and work, and better understand the Cowells’ professional contributions and personal lives.
Sidney Robertson first visited the Archive of American Folk Song, then housed in the Library’s Music Division, in 1936, to discuss some points about American folksong. Her interest led to meetings with Charles Seeger, who hired her to collect and record folk music for the New Deal’s Resettlement Administration. Through her work with Seeger, her ties to various Archive heads, and with Harold Spivacke, chief of the Music Division, were strengthened. Much of the fieldwork done at the Resettlement Administration is now part of the Library’s collections.
The Work Projects Administration California Folk Music Project, conceived and managed by Sidney Robertson Cowell, was jointly sponsored by the Music Department of the University of California, Berkeley and the Library of Congress. Harold Spivacke provided important support by supplying Cowell with blank acetate discs on which to record--with the provision that these recordings be given to the Library—and offering cataloging guidance. The original field recordings became part of the Archive of American Folk Song in 1939 and 1940. These recordings and other materials from the project form the core of the American Folklife Center's W.P.A. California Folk Music Project Collection. In addition, some of the recordings that Sidney made on field trips at home and abroad, including Rockefeller Foundation trips to Asia with Henry, reside in the American Folklife Center.
Henry Cowell began depositing his music manuscripts with the Library in the 1940s. Through Henry and Sidney’s generosity, the Music Division would ultimately hold the majority of Henry Cowell’s holograph music manuscripts, which number about 1100 items and date from 1907 to 1965, the year he died. The other repository holding any sizable number of these is the New York Public Library for the Performing Arts, which also holds most of Henry Cowell’s personal papers. His music manuscripts at the Library of Congress have been cataloged under the Library of Congress call number ML96.C823, with the exception of works commissioned by various Music Division foundations and a group of folksongs, with accompaniments in Henry Cowell’s hand, located in the Sidney Robertson Cowell Collection. Additional material relating to Henry Cowell, including correspondence and some writings, can be found in numerous collections throughout the Music Division.
Sidney kept in close contact with former Library of Congress Music Division chiefs Harold Spivacke and Don Leavitt, and others within the division, throughout the remainder of her life. Not only did she oversee the Henry Cowell manuscript donations, but she regularly made donations of her own personal and professional papers which comprise the Sidney Robertson Cowell Collection in the Library of Congress and are described in this finding aid.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Other Repositories
The other major repository of Sidney Robertson Cowell material is the Music Library of the University of California, Berkeley. The California Folk Music Project Records, 1938-1942 were a gift by the local Work Projects Administration in 1942. The collection includes administrative documents; English translations of articles on folk music; material on music in the California missions; lists of California songsters and hymnals; song texts with references to California; material on Portuguese, Spanish, and Latin American folk songs; sketches, scale drawings, and tracings of folk instruments; sound tape reel copies of performances, and original glass sound discs. There are also 3x5 card file indexes of known recordings, photographs of performers, instruments, songsters, hymnals, and bibliographies.
The New York Public Library holds the Henry Cowell Papers and additional materials related to Sidney Robertson Cowell.
The Ralph Rinzler Folklife Archives and Collections housed in the Smithsonian Institution's Smithsonian Center for Folklife and Cultural Heritage contains duplicates of some of Cowell's Ireland recordings.
Related Material
Additional material relating to Sidney Robertson Cowell is in the following collections in the Library of Congress Music Division: Charles Seeger Collection,
Nicolas Slonimsky Collection
,
Modern Music Archives
, and Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge Foundation Collection. Additional correspondence to and from Sidney Robertson Cowell is located in Music Division Old Correspondence and in a small collection that is cataloged separately under ML94.C69.
The American Folklife Center (AFC) of the Library of Congress holds significant primary source material by and relating to Sidney Robertson Cowell, primarily sound recordings accessioned into AFC’s Archive beginning in 1937. The Resettlement Administration Recordings Collection contains 165 field recordings of instrumentals and songs recorded in 1936 and 1937, in various states, by Cowell and others for the Resettlement Administration. It also includes her 1937 recordings of performances at the Fourth Annual National Folk Festival, in Chicago. The W.P.A. California Folk Music Project Collection in the AFC spans 1936 to 1991 and contains 239 discs that Cowell gave to the Archive of American Folk Song at the Library in 1939 and 1940. This collection surveys traditional music and folk song of many ethnic groups in northern California and also includes publicity materials, correspondence, song texts/transcriptions, notes on songs, interview forms, field reports, 170 photographic prints, and twenty-four drawings of instruments. A substantial portion is available online (see Online Content below). The recordings that Cowell made of Carrie Grover from Gorham, Maine also reside in the AFC. These recordings of folk songs, ballads and popular songs were recorded in Teaneck, New Jersey, in 1941.
The AFC has several additional collections related to Sidney Robertson Cowell. There are twelve tapes of folk music recorded in Ireland, Iran, Pakistan and Malaya in the mid-1950s accompanied by additional documentation. The Sidney Robertson Cowell Collection of Writings and Reminiscences contains her recollections about doing fieldwork and folksong collecting. It ranges from the 1950s to 1990 and includes additional biographical, music, and research material. Eight tapes of folksongs recorded by Maud Karpeles and Cowell in North Carolina, Tennessee and Virginia in 1950 reside in the AFC along with accompanying documentation. AFC holds fourteen tapes of interviews and music recorded from 1952 to 1956 in Bangladesh, California, Canada, Iran, Ireland, Massachusetts, Montana, New York, North Carolina, Nova Scotia, Pakistan, Wisconsin and Wyoming. This collection also includes correspondence, journals, logs, notes, postcards, transcriptions, and articles. In addition, there is one tape of Wisconsin fiddle tunes originally recorded on disc in 1937 and one disc containing songs sung by Ford-Walker family members recorded in Wisconsin in 1937.
Please contact the Folklife Reading Room, Library of Congress at folklife@loc.gov for more information about these Sidney Robertson Cowell collections.
Access and Restrictions
The Sidney Robertson Cowell Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Online Content
The American Folklife Center of the Library of Congress has digitized and made available a large portion of their W.P.A. California Folk Music Project Collection. California Gold: Northern California Folk Music from the Thirties (http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/afccchtml/cowhome.html) includes sound recordings, still photographs, drawings, and written documents from a variety of European ethnic and English- and Spanish-speaking communities in Northern California.
The Traditional Music and Spoken Word Catalog from the American Folklife Center (http://memory.loc.gov/diglib/ihas/html/afccards/afccards-home.html) provides title and bibliographic information for many of Sidney Robertson Cowell’s ethnographic sound recordings accessioned in the Archive of American Folk Song up until about 1950.
The Wisconsin Folksong Collection, 1937-1946 (http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/WiscFolkSong/#) contains recordings collected by Sidney Robertson Cowell during the summer of 1937 for the Resettlement Administration. These recordings were digitized from the original discs at the Library of Congress American Folklife Center.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1903 June 2 Born Sidney William Hawkins, San Francisco, California
1917 Met Henry Cowell for the first time
1922-1923 French government exchange student at the Lycée de jeunes filles, Tours, France
1924 B.A., Romance Languages, Stanford University, Palo Alto, Calif. Married Kenneth Robertson (divorced 1933)
1925 Studied analytic psychology with Carl Jung, Zurich, Switzerland
1925-1926 Studied piano with Alfred Cortot, Ecole normale de musique, Paris, France
1926-circa 1932 Music teacher, head of music department, Peninsula School, Palo Alto, Calif.
1927-1930 Studied music theory with Ernest Bloch, San Francisco Conservatory of Music and with Charles Koechlin, Berkeley, Calif.
1932 Studied piano with Harold Bauer in California
1935-1936 Studied music with Henry Cowell, New York City Head of social music, Henry Street Settlement, N.Y. Notated songs of elderly Jews, New York City
1936 Music assistant to Charles Seeger, KL Division, Music Unit, Special Skills Division, Resettlement Administration (RA), Washington, D.C. Accompanied John Lomax and Frank C. Brown on recording trip to western North Carolina where she assisted in recording melismatic singing and African-American singing in chain gang road camps for the RA Collected and recorded traditional singers and music in Arkansas, Maryland, Missouri, North Carolina, Pennsylvania, South Carolina, Tennessee, and Virginia for the RA
1937 Regional representative, Special Skills Division, Resettlement Administration Recorded in Minnesota and Northern Wisconsin (including Warde Ford and his extended family) Relief community manager, Special Services Section, Region 2 (Wis., Minn., Mich.), Farm Security Administration Recorded Finnish, Serbian and Gaelic communities in Great Lakes states Recorded Swedish, Lithuanian, Norwegian and Finnish musicians at the Fourth National Folk Festival in Chicago, Ill. Recorded lumberjacks in Michigan Began to develop folksong collecting projects through New Deal arts organizations and private grants organizations Began folk music research in her native California
1938 WPA approved California Folk Music Project co-sponsored by Library of Congress and the University of California, Berkeley California Folk Music Project officially opened (brought to a close in 1940)
1939 Founder of Archive of California Folk Music, University of California, Berkeley
1940 Published with Eleanora Black The Gold Rush Song Book. San Francisco: Colt Press
1941 Consultant in folk music, Music Division, Pan American Union, Washington, D.C. Married Henry Cowell (died 1965) Recorded Carrie Grover of Gorham, Maine in Teaneck, N.J.
1942 Published with Alan Lomax American Folk Song and Folk Lore: A Regional Bibliography. New York: Progressive Education Association Moved to Shady, New York
1942-circa 1950 Music instructor, Mills College of Education, N.Y.
1950 American correspondent, International Folk Music Council Presented folk performers at the Ditson Festival of American Music at Columbia University, N.Y. Accompanied by Maud Karpeles, re-recorded singers in Appalachians who had performed for Cecil Sharp
1950-1951 Visiting lecturer during the summers, University of Southern California
1952-1955 Recorded Ford-Walker family in Crandon, Wisconsin; California; Wyoming; and Germany
1953 Recorded American Folk Music Concert at the Sixth Annual Festival of Contemporary American Music, Columbia University, N.Y. Recorded bagpipe tunes and Scottish Gaelic singing on Cape Breton Island, Nova Scotia Recorded Spanish and Persian singing in Alameda and Berkeley, California
1954 Published with Henry Cowell Charles Ives and His Music. New York: Oxford University Press
1954-1960 Instructor, New School, New York, N.Y.
1955 Instructor, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass. Published with John P. Hughes Songs from Cape Breton Island. New York: Folkways Records
1955-1956 Traveled with Henry Cowell to Europe and Asia on State Department assignments Recorded in the Aran Islands and Carna, Connemara, Ireland Recorded traditional music in Iran, Thailand, Pakistan, and Malaya
1956 Published Wolf River Songs. New York: Folkways Records
1956-1957 Travelled to several Asian countries with Henry Cowell on Rockefeller Foundation grant to report on status of traditional and classical music in Asia Recorded music in Asia and Iran
1957 Published Songs of Aran. New York: Folkways Records
1995 Feb. 23 Died, Shady, New York
Scope and Content Note
The Sidney Robertson Cowell Collection, numbering more than 5,000 items, contains material from her work as a folk song collector and ethnographer; voluminous correspondence to her family, friends and colleagues--many of whom are prominent figures in 20th century American music--published and unpublished essays, reviews, and articles; biographical narratives; instructional materials from various stints as a music teacher, and an extensive subject file. The collection contains a great amount of information on Sidney Robertson Cowell’s husband, modernist composer Henry Cowell, including material pertaining to their marriage, writings by and about him, material dealing with his professional relationships with other notables in the music world, and documents concerning his musical legacy, which was carefully nurtured by Sidney Robertson Cowell.
A large part of the collection deals with two major aspects of Cowell’s life: her innovative and groundbreaking work as an ethnographer and folksong and ethnic music collector and recordist; as well as her role as husband Henry Cowell’s personal and professional partner and proprietor of his musical legacy. The extensive fieldwork materials she collected exemplify Sidney Robertson Cowell’s keen insights into the people and music she encountered and offer a behind-the-scenes look at the history and process of her work. The collection is also rich in material that details Cowell’s complex life with Henry Cowell, whom she married in 1941. There is material dealing with their personal lives as well as extensive material related to their writing and travelling collaborations and business and publishing ventures. After Henry Cowell’s death in 1965, Sidney took charge of his personal and professional reputation, which is reflected in correspondence and other material from the 1970s through the 1990s. The collection consists of nine series: Correspondence, Materials Relating to Fieldwork, Materials Relating to Henry Cowell, Biographical Material, Writings and Publications, Subject Files, Photographs, Teaching Materials, and Songs and Song Books.
The Correspondence series is divided into two subseries: Personal (non-family) and Professional Correspondence; and Family Correspondence. The first series covers a myriad of topics with a primary focus on professional matters. Correspondence with Suzanne Bloch, John Cage, Merce Cunningham, Lukas Foss, Alfred Frankenstein, Lou Harrison, Colin McPhee, Ned Rorem, and Virgil Thomson concerns professional projects and interests, and offers personal news and viewpoints. Issues relating to Henry Cowell, such as music publishing, discographical entries, and biographical topics are the focus of extensive correspondence with H. Wiley Hitchcock, John Kirkpatrick, William Lichtenwanger, Bruce Saylor, and others. A large amount of the Lichtenwanger and Hitchcock correspondence deals with the catalog of Henry Cowell’s music, which was compiled by Lichtenwanger and published by Hitchcock’s Institute for the Study of American Music. Richard Franko Goldman, Nicolas Slonimsky, and Hugo Weisgall are also frequent correspondents. Sidney Robertson Cowell maintained relationships with many notables in the folk music field, including Bertrand Bronson, Sam Eskin, Charles, Peggy and Pete Seeger, and Margaret Valiant, all of whom are represented in this subseries.
The second subseries, Family Correspondence, contains correspondence with several family members, including Cowell’s parents Charles Hawkins and Mabel “Muz” Morrison Hawkins; husbands Henry Cowell and Kenneth Robertson; siblings Charles Ernest Hawkins, John “Bud” Hawkins, Anne Cotton, and Jeane Mibach; and Henry Cowell’s stepmother, Olive Cowell. Letters to her family, particularly to her mother, shed light on Cowell’s early life during the 1910s, 1920s, and 1930s. Extensive correspondence with her sister Anne captures Cowell’s thoughts and feelings on a host of personal and professional topics. In addition, these letters contain a great deal of information about relatives and ancestors from both the Hawkins and Morrison sides of her family.
The Materials Relating to Fieldwork series deals with Cowell’s major folksong and ethnographic music collecting and recording projects. Contained therein are not only finished reports, articles, and song lists derived from these activities, but also handwritten diaries, fieldnotes, letters and draft reports that reveal personal and procedural details about the projects. The series is divided into nine sections. The Resettlement Administration Field Trip to North Carolina with John Lomax section chronicles Cowell’s summer 1936 trip to Western North Carolina with John Lomax and Frank Brown. Cowell was hired in 1936 as Charles Seeger’s music assistant in the Special Skills Division of the Resettlement Administration (RA). Although she had already done some field collecting, Seeger wanted her to become better acquainted with the recording equipment and to benefit from Lomax and Brown’s field experience. The material includes her fieldnotes, correspondence that provides context and background information on the trip, and the final report for the RA.